Pokémon Diamond, Pearl and Platinum is the fourth generation of Pokémo-
What is that thing?
If that thing was real, it would be terrifying.
[Garbage Guide Intro SFX]
I could only pick Platinum.
Not because I asked Twitter,
but because, diamonds exist because a dinosaur buried some coal -
the WORST fossil fuel -
and pearls are just oyster saliva.
A lot of it.
The game begins with Professor Ro-Han -
they never show what university he teaches at, so I don't believe he's a real professor -
explaining Pokémon.
Then pick gender.
I picked a girl, because of her clothes:
no pants, perfect for summer;
but a scarf, for winter.
Ready for every weather!
Name... Her real name is
DAWN.
Which is a COOL name.
Too cool for me.
I could name her "Diamond" - because, you know, ♪Diamonds are a girl's best friend!♪ -
but I'm a proud, beautiful WOMAN.
What's a WOMAN'S best friend?
So I named her "Wine".
Wine is watching a TV program about Rowan,
gets bored and wants to go to bed.
Unfortunately, her rival,
DRAGAZO, THE CONQUEROR,
shows up.
In previous games, the rival has been a douche, and forgettable...
here, he's a mental case, and says we should go and force Professor Rowan to give us Pokémon.
I don't want to help this psycho, so I go back to bed.
Then I remember my friend might stab the Professor, so I reluctantly leave.
The duo makes it to some tall grass. Too dangerous to step on.
Oh my god! This motherfucker's gonna jump it!
Professor Rowan stops him from breaking a world record.
Prof. Rowan (German accent):
"You kids want to know why the population in towns are so low?"
"Because wild Pokémon eat children."
"As a Pokémon Professor, I've filmed it."
His assistant gives us our Pokémon.
I don't know what to pick- a Penginn!
That's the most socially awkward, cringey animal in the animal kingdom!
The rivals fight. He keeps using Withdraw,
making it the slowest-
IT'S BEEN DAYS.
Dragazo suggests they go to the lake. Apparently it has a legendary Pokémon.
There, they meet a blue-haired guy who's talking to the water.
(Guy: "Hello Lake. I'm An Energy Man.")
Both agree, things got too weird.
(Guy: "You As A Lake Can Provide Energy-")
Wine has been called to the Pokémon Lab, so she can't sleep just yet.
Prof. Rowan:
"Fill out mein Pokédex. No one ever does, but I'm sure you will."
Finally, the adventure actually starts.
Go to the first city. Here we meet INTERPOL.
Fucking INTERPOL. We've reached the first city and already the game has lost it.
Clowns give you a watch.
Yes, it's 4am, what do you want from me?
What else is this company developing?
The PedoMeter.
I have to get out of here.
As I was trying to leave, our insane friend stops us again
AND HE KEEPS USING WITHDRAW!
I need a Fire Pokémon...
It's too early to find one: Fire Pokémons in forests ARE guaranteed to cause wildfires.
Maybe I can ask someone for it...
"Hello Professor Oak. Please send me fire."
Now we wait...
♪Stock Music♪
Oak:
"I Lve Wine"
"burp..."
"heav a birb"
Okay! This will do!
That's four birds! I'm becoming a bird guy!
Hypothetical YouTube Commenter:
"kilian that's a beaver-"
Actually, every Pokémon lays eggs, that makes them all birds.
Our rival was heading to Oreburgh City, so I guess we are too.
Enter a cave.
This guy asks us if we want to Rock Smash.
I don't think he's talking about the attack.
Oreburgh City: a mining town.
This entire place is giving me lung cancer, so let's go kill this gym.
Wait, a coal museum?
That's the best fossil fuel!
I care way more about this than Pocket Animals™!
The Gym Leader isn't here, because he has a job in the coal mine.
♪Triumphant Music♪
Gym Leaders aren't making enough money, so he has to sacrifice his lungs.
Vote Worker Mason for a better Sinnoh.
Meet up with the Leader, and he shows you how to use Rock Smash.
I knew that guy was a pervert!
First Gym, didn't take any damage.
Rock is weak against Water. Why?
Ever seen the Grand Canyon? A small river did that.
Imagine what THIS can do against a rock.
On our way to the next town, we, for the first time, encounter Team Galactic.
In previous games, we've faced kidnappers and Lex Luthor;
this time, it's an energy company, a much realer evil than previous games.
Cyrus is their CEO.
We move through here and reach Flower-Power-Tower Town, a city famous for its...
porn industry.
Just outside, we meet a daughter, whose dad has been kidnapped.
Instead of becoming an action hero, she asks me to take care of it.
Pathetic.
What happened is that the energy company has taken over a wind power plant and is torturing the owner.
I-I'm sorry, this is getting way too real.
Enter the power plant; here we face one of the Galactic Leaders.
Mars:
"Hello, I am Mars. My parents knew I would be a bitch, so they named me after the god of war."
"We at Team Galactic are trying to create a better world than this one."
Wine:
"Have you tried recycling?"
Mars:
"Not. What I meant. Let's Pokémon Battle."
Her final Pokémon is a ripped cat... N-No joke, just look at it.
The kidnapped dad tells us they're trying to gather electricity to create a new universe.
No they're not. They are fucking with you.
INTERPOL shows up too late and tells us to go to Eterna City.
♪Hillbilly Music♪
We're here! And the music tells us this is a pretty backwards place...
There's that Cyrus guy again... and now he's talking to a statue.
(Cyrus: "Hello Statue. You See, I'm An Energy Man.")
Cynthia, another main character, tells us,
(Cyrus, offscreen: "You Are An Ancient Statue.")
Cynthia:
"That Pokémon appeared here ages ago and told the inhabitants to marry their own cousin."
"Things might have been changed a bit to fit a narrative."
Galactic has an HQ here, with trees in front of it.
Here's an artist's rendition.
To cut down trees, we need to beat the Grass Gym.
Water is weak against Grass, but my Pengalingaling is pretty overpowered.
She destroyed me... uh, so I pretend to fall from this clock, and threatened her with a lawsuit.
Thaaank you!
Cut trees; we've beaten Mars, here we face another Galactic Leader.
Snickers.
But before I faced her, I remembered...
I don't care about this.
Who placed all these bikes outside like this?
Someone could steal one.
Now we can travel on the Bike Road, all the way down to a cave entrance.
Inside the cave, we meet Cyrus, who just complains about humanity. Has no real reason be here...
(Cyrus: Hello Girl. I Hate Humanity. You See, I'm An Energy Man.)
Ahhh, Hearthome City.
Our mum works here and gives us a dress,
not realising that if it weren't for these clothes, she wouldn't even have a daughter.
I wanna live with Dad!
Whoever that is!
The Hearthome Gym is a Ghost Gym.
But ghosts aren't real, so that was easy!
Dragazo stops us outside and that's almost half the video, let's talk about what you REALLY want to hear about.
My favourite episode is when a Godzilla bug kills a trans alien and destroys a dimension.
Why is dubbed Digimon such a masterpiece, while Japanese TERRIBLE-mon is not?
Oh, the egg Cynthia gave me is hatching.
And it's, uh... That's a weird bird.
But it's the most generic-looking Pokémon I've ever seen.
Veil-Shtone, has a shopping mall,
but I'm poor;
has the Galactic HQ;
and has meteorites, that almost perfectly hit the city.
Michael Bay called it!
And the Gym. Here comes the biggest shock in Pokémon history:
this Gym... is an actual gym.
WHAT.
WHAT. THE.
WHAT. THE. FUCK.
It's one of the hardest gyms in the game...
I also had problems with it, until I remembered that it's a Fighting Gym,
so Wine can fight herself.
[punching sound effects]
(Original scene from Ip Man (2008))
Doctor Rowan's assistant wants us to break into Team Galactic's warehouse.
That's very illegal,
but I'm a tired gangster.
The more I see Team Galactic, the more I think, real energy companies should do this.
If Shell started calling themselves Team Shell, and got matching hairdos and started talking about catching gods,
no one would care about oil-drilling scandals.
We reach a beach town.
There's nothing to do here.
Still took me 30 minutes to figure out where to go:
to the neighbour town, Pastaoria City.
Or in the Japanese version,
Ramenoria City.
Enter the Gym; the intro guy says:
Intro Guy (high-pitched, faltering):
"Don't step in the water!"
"We all pissed in it!"
"This Gym doesn't have any bathrooms!"
"You can step on platform and raise water levels!"
"This Gym is terrible for the environment!"
I don't want to be here.
Wine:
"Hello, I'm a pool safety inspector,"
"and I take bribes!"
Get the Badge and leave.
THEN THERE'S A TERRORIST ATTACK!!!
What happened to Pokémon?
The terrorist defends himself by saying,
"I didn't kill anyone, the bomb killed people!"
Wake:
"Wine, you run after him; meanwhile, I'll try to do nothing."
INTERPOL shows up and says that was probably a member of Team Galactic.
*sigh* I hate you. I really do.
Finally, we catch up to him, and then he runs away.
What was the point of chasing him?
Cynthia shows up...
Cynthia:
"Wanna go cure some ducks for me?"
Wine:
"No?"
Cynthia:
"Here's the medicine, I'm going to the beach."
Why do I even do things?
This opens up to go to Celestic Town.
Cynthia's grandmother tells us to fight a Galactic Grunt protecting a cave.
*slap* *slap* *slap*
And I slap the shit out of him.
In the cave we see paintings, and the grandmother explains,
it's godlike jellyfish.
Cyrus shows up...
Cyrus:
"Hello Grandmother."
"I Like Jellyfishes."
"You See, They Are Energy Fishes."
"At Least, According To Finding Nemo."
Then he challenges me.
I say no.
He actually listens, and teleports away. Never described how...
Ride on water; get to Cave-Latte, a boat town.
Our rival challenges us on a drawbridge.
In the middle of battle, a boat passes and almost kills us both.
The local Gym is a construction site. Obviously, the sound here is muted,
*voice gradually drowned out by construction noises*
but if I turn it up, thIS IS WHAT IT SOUNDS LIKE.
We did it! We got the move Strength.
Now I need a bird that can use it,
but the only one is Magmar, and that's a DUCK.
I dislike DUCKS.
I guess THIS thing is bird enough...
We meet up with Dragazo and the others at the library.
Finally, a chance to take a nap...
AND THEN THERE'S ANOTHER TERRORIST ATTACK!!!
This time, at Lake Valor.
Rowan tells Wine to "Go there and take on the terrorists!"
Wine:
"Why me?"
"Why not the adults?"
Prof. Rowan:
"Because they are supposed to go to 'Lake Not-Main-Character-So-No-One-Cares'."
Okay, they blew up the water and kill a lot of Magikarps.
And probably all local wildlife.
This guy says the next target, so fuck it, let's go there.
Apparently Team Galactic are after the Legendary Jellyfishes.
Hey, Mars is here! And she still has the swole cat!
We're too late. They got the Fish.
Only one lake left, and it requires me to
walk kilometres through a winter wonderland
and defeat the hardest FUCKING Gym Leader ever,
get Rock Climb,
I don't have a bird that can use it,
the only bird that can is Magmar, but Magmar can't FLY, and what kind of bird ca-
hah...
what kind of bird doesn't have wings?
This entire trip has taken seven hours, no way-
THEY ARE STILL THERE.
WHY WEREN'T YOU THIS LAZY AT THE OTHER LOCATIONS?
Still too late. They have gathered all the jellyfishes.
Let's attack the Galactic HQ head-on.
No!
That's a really dumb idea, and if we get caught it's six months for breaking and entering!
Let's do it the legal way!
Wine:
"Hello, here to see Cyrus."
Cyrus:
"Hello, I Want To Destroy This World."
Cyrus is inspiring his troops, but I can't focus because I just now noticed,
(Cyrus: "You See, If I Have A Universe, And YOU Have A Universe,")
is Team Galactic wearing wigs? Or is there a Team Galactic Hairdresser?
(Cyrus: "And I Have A Straw, That Goes From MY Universe To YOUR Universe, I DRINK-")
Then he goes into an elevator,
and I'm left wondering, he just admitted to wanting to destroy the world, can't INTERPOL arrest him now?
Nope, still my job.
There he is. Probably gonna try to convince me to join him.
Cyrus:
"I Don't Want You To Join Me."
Wine:
"Rude..."
Cyrus:
"But Still. Professor Rowan Never Told You What Happened To Your Father."
Wine:
"No, I don't think he knew him."
♪Star Wars Imperial March♪
Cyrus:
"No. I. Am Your Father."
[music stops]
Wine:
"Okay, makes sense, not a lot of men on this island."
[music resumes]
Cyrus:
"You Know It To Be True."
"I Left Your Mother Because She Was An Alcoholic."
"She Named You 'Wine', For God's Sake."
He leaves, and gives us the fishies. How nice of him!
Oh right, he's gonna destroy the world.
SHIT SHIT SHIT SHIT SHITSHITSHITSHI-
We have to get to the top of Mount Morenet, fast!
I was stuck in this place for almost an hour.
*out of breath*
I made it... Imma stop you...Hey it's those two, I can take on them both...
Oh no, Dragazo showed up and he's... I have to team up with him and he's useless...
Then shit goes down:
Cyrus summons Pokémon gods, then the Jellyfishes shows up,
a hole opens up, and THIS thing attacks the DS and destroys it.
Now there's a portal to another world.
Cynthia:
"You have to go in there, to saaave the universe!"
Wine:
"I don't wanna."
"I just wanted to see what my friend was up to,"
"now I have to save the world?"
"[desparate] I just wanted to sleep! I've been awake for 31 hours!"
Welcome to the Disorientation World,
it's a very weird place where the law-
ylppa t'nod scisyhp oslA
After a long and weird journey, and a final battle with Cyrus, you face...
THAT thing. A legendary Pokemon from another world, capable of destroying the universe.
Throw some bubbles at him.
He has to DIE because he's not a BIRD.
We did it! We saved the galaxy! Time to do something more important:
take on the Pokémon League.
There's one more Gym in Sun-Shore;
there's a subplot that deals with depression -
this game is not E For Everyone -
it's an Electricity Gym; obviously Flying is weak against Electricity,
But I still beat Naruto on my first try, because I was in another dimension earlier today.
Victory Road! I was hoping this would be the game where they remove it!
We made it to the Pokémon League!
A-Aaron's bugs,
Bertha's... Ground(?),
and Volkner's non-air-conditioned room,
were all weak against Pengling's attacks.
Then there was a Psychic master!
It was a slaughter. I defeated him with barely anything left.
The final Trainer is...
Cynthia!
We all saw that coming!
Cynthia:
"Professor Rowan never told you what happened to your aunt."
No... This is impossible... I will lose unless...
♪Flash Gordon theme starts playing♪
unless something saves me in the last second.
Garchomp:
"General Cynthia, Magmar approaching!"
Cynthia:
"What do you mean, 'Magmar approaching'?"
♪MAG!♪
♪MAAAR!♪
♪HE'S FOR EVERY ONE OF US!♪
♪STANDS FOR EVERY ONE OF US!♪
♪HE'LL SAVE YOU WITH A MIGHTY HAND, EVERY MAN, EVERY WOMAN, EVERY CHILD, WITH A MAG MAGMAR!♪
What an epic journey, but it's finally over.
Actually, no, Platinum has a lot of endgame content -
this entire island! -
but no, I've done my part.
Time to go to bed now.
And THAT is the Kilian Experience.
♪Outro Music - "Rickety Roadster (Theme)" by Purple Planet♪